Finding Aid for Emerson R. Smith papers, 1859-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emerson R. Smith papers 1859-1964, 1956-1962
Smith, Emerson R.
3 linear feet
8627 Aa 2
St. Ignace, Michigan local historian; correspondence, genealogical and historical materials concerning Native Americans and the French in and around the Straits of Mackinac, particularly in St. Ignace and on Mackinac Island.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Emerson R. Smith (donor no. 3421 ) and came to the library in 1968.
The collection is open to research.
Emerson R. Smith was born and raised in St. Ignace, Michigan in 1892. He attended the University of Michigan and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1913. Mr. Smith worked for the Eastern Branch of the National Underwriter Company in New York until 1931, when he took a position as supervisor of the Ordinary Department of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company of New York. While in New York, he served two years as the Editor of the Gothamite, a publication of the University of Michigan Club of New York. He retired to his hometown of St. Ignace in the Year 1954, spending his retirement years as the president of the Michilimackinac Historical Society. He was an active member of the Kiwanis Club, the Masonic Lodge, the Garden Club, and the St. Ignace Methodist Church. He died in 1963.
The Emerson R. Smith papers mostly consist of correspondence and reference materials pertaining to the history of the Straits area of Michigan (St. Ignace, Mackinaw City and Mackinac Island).
Subjects:
Bedell family.; Fort de Buade (Mich.); Fort Mackinac (Mackinac Island, Mich.); Fort Michilimackinac (Mackinaw City, Mich.); Fortification--Michigan.; French Americans--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; La Salle, Robert Cavelier, sieur de, 1643-1687.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Marquette, Jacques, 1637-1675.; Methodist Church (Saint Ignace, Mich.); Michigan--Bibliography.; Michigan. Civil War Centennial Observance Commission.; Michigan--History.; Moran (Mich.: Township); Names, Geographical.; Saint Ignace (Mich.); Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Antiques--Michigan.; Castle Rock (Saint Ignace, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Saint Ignace.; Ferries.; Graveraet family.; Historical markers.; Indians of North America--Michigan--Arts and crafts.; Interiors.; Marine accidents.; Monuments and memorials.; Saint Ignace (Mich.); Saint Ignace (Mich.)--Churches.; Smith, Emerson R.; Tourism.
Contributors:
Baird, Elizabeth Therese Fisher, 1810-1890.; Dever, Harry.; Greenlees, Orr.; Michilimackinac Historical Society.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Much of the Correspondence revolves around the discussion of historic controversies concerning the Straits region. Smith's historical investigations often brought him into conflict with the Mackinac Island State Park Commission, headed by W. S. Woodfill, owner of the Grand Hotel, who he believed to be fabricating history to serve the economic interests of Mackinac Island.
  Also included in the Correspondence series are communications with Harry Dever, a self-proclaimed authority on native languages and customs, who served as an ally in Mr. Smith's fight for accurate portrayal of local history.
  - 1937 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1956-1963, 26 folders (Box 1)
  - Dever, Harry 1960-1962 (Box 1)
- Research Files and Collected Historical Materials
  The Research Files and Collected Historical Materials series contains topical files pertaining to local history, largely regarding the Indians and French in the area of the Straits of Mackinac, particularly St. Ignace and Mackinac Island. The establishment of historical markers in the region, research materials and information regarding various controversies form the bulk of the material. Also included are materials gathered to support the celebration of the Civil War centennial and to support the publication of the book " Before the Bridge" and the Kiwanis Publication " Our Local History".
  - Baird, Elizabeth T., Manuscript and Correspondence Regarding 1898, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographic Information Including Extracts Concerning Area History, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Birding (Box 1)
  - Brevort 1961 (Box 1)
  - Civil War
    - Civil War letters 1861-1864 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Civil War Centennial Celebration Commission 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Controversies
    - Biddle Family 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Origin and Meaning of Michilimackinac 1957-1960 (Box 2)
    - Origin of Michigan Names 1957-1960 (Box 2)
    - St. Ignace as Ile de Michilimackinac 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Forts
    - Ft. De Baude 1957-1961 (Box 2)
    - Ft. Michilimackinac 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Geenlees, Orr 1913-1916 (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Research Project, University of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Gros Cap 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Historical Markers 1958 (Box 2)
  - Historical Personalities
    - Henry, Alexander (Box 2)
    - LaSalle and the Griffon 1956-1961 (Box 2)
    - Father Marquette 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Kiwanis (Box 2)
  - Mackinac Bridge (Box 2)
  - Mackinaw Island 1950-1960 (Box 2)
  - Mackinaw Island Park Commission 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Michilimackinac Historic Society 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Native Americans
    - Native American Burial Ground 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Native American History 1957-1962 (Box 2)
    - Native American Languages 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Native American Use of Plants 1960 (Box 2)
  - Poetry and Music (Box 2)
  - St. Ignace
    - Genealogical information for St. Ignace Residents 1955-1962 (Box 2)
    - General 1956-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Methodist Church (Box 2)
  - Sault Ste. Marie (petitions to Governor Moses Wisner) 1859-1860, photostats of original and typescript (Box 2)
  - Smith, Emerson
    - Awards and Citations (Box 3)
    - "Before the Bridge" (Box 3)
    - Handwritten Notes and Outlines (Box 3)
    - Radio Talk, WCBY 1960 (Box 3)
    - Essays 1961, undated (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains local maps and photographs documenting historic events, sites and artifacts in and from the region.
  - Maps 1958, undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains newspaper clippings documenting the effort to develop an historical identity for the region, as well as a local column entitled "Bird Corner", to which Mr. Smith was a regular contributor. The series also contains materials published by local historic sites and organizations interested in the history of the region.
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Loose, unsorted, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Mackinaw Bridge 1957-1960 (Box 3)
    - Birding (Box 3)
    - Notebooks with Newspaper Clippings (Box 3)
  - Publication Extracts (Box 3)